What if I were to tell you that one of
the most dangerous things isn't
necessarily food or stress or aging?
It's actually the lighting inside your
house. The lighting in your house might
sound like a very trivial thing. And the
reason why so many people don't even see
this is because it's been normalized.
Everyone uses it and it doesn't even
feel dangerous at all. And this one
single environmental mismatch. And when
I talk about mismatches, I'm talking
about comparing way back in the day when
our environment was very, very different
compared to modern day. And out of all
the mismatches, light is at the top of
the list because light affects something
called the circadian system. This has to
do with your mood, your metabolism, your
hormones, and you can be eating fine and
actually exercising and sleeping enough,
but still have a problem if your
lighting isn't correct. Your circadian
rhythm is a clock, okay? And it's
controlled by light and dark signals.
But you also have different clocks in
different organs in the body. And
they're all synced by this master clock
in your brain. And so this circadian
system is on a rhythm. And the most
important thing about it is this one
word right here, contrast. Light and
dark. Way back in the day, we were
exposed to very bright light during the
day and also when the sun set, we were
exposed to darkness. And out of that,
this system was created called the
circadian rhythm that we're still
operating off of. But unfortunately, in
the modern environment, we don't have
this contrast anymore. But before I get
into this very interesting subject, I
first need to define a new word. You may
know it or you may not. It's called Lux.
And Lux has to do with how bright a
light is. Even on your phone, you can
actually get an app, a lux meter. And
you can actually measure how much
brightness from a light is hitting this
surface right here or on your body if
you hold it very closely. When we get
into the outdoors and you're being
exposed to the sun, depending on where
you are and if there's clouds out, you
might be exposed to 10,000 to up to a
100,000
lux. On an overcast day, that goes down
to 2,000 to 10,000. When you're indoors,
it can go from 100 to 500, sometimes
even more, depending on the lights that
you're exposed to. At nighttime using
your phone or watching your TV, that can
be between 300 and a,000 lux. When
you're outside and you're exposed to the
moonlight, it's very tiny lux, 0.1.
Okay, it's almost nothing. And then we
have other things like your fireplace
which is like 50s very very small
amounts of lux. Because of the current
modern-day lighting situation we have
created the absolute worst environment
for our human brains that ever was. And
we created this artificial environment
where the days are very dim but the
nights are very bright. We also have
filtered sunlight through glass because
glass is insulated with a gas that
prevents UV and infrared. This lack of
light signal tells the brain it's not
daytime. Okay, that's the signal that
our brains get. Then at night, we have
overhead LEDs. In one of the rooms in my
house, we actually have all these LED
lights, very bright, very unnatural, and
then you have TVs, phones, tablets, very
strong signals that tell our brains to
stay alert and stay awake. So during the
morning part of the day, we don't have
the signals to wake up. Yet at night, we
do have the signals to wake up. So
that's what I mean by contrast.
Everything is kind of grayed out, kind
of neutralized. There's no big huge
difference between morning and night.
It's kind of the same, but usually at
night you have to turn the lights up
because it gets dark outside. So this is
creating not just a mild problem for our
brain, it's creating a major problem for
our brain. Even if you compare that to
staying up late, it doesn't even
compare. This lack of contrast is much
more damaging to our circadian waves.
Historically, humans have been outside
in the bright light. Farmers are outside
a great majority of the day. And even
when we had winters, when the days were
shorter and it got dark sooner, we still
had campfires. We had fire at night,
which is very nondisruptive. if it's
very low lux. So modern day dark days,
bright lights, huge disruption. This
affects melatonin release. Melatonin is
a hormone that tells you it's time to go
to sleep. I'm tired. And it helps you
get to sleep. So melatonin is either
delayed or it's blunted. You have a
problem with cortisol because cortisol
is triggered by blue light. And you
might lie in bed for 7 or 8 hours, but
the depth of sleep is missing. When you
go to bed at night, you go through four
cycles of sleep from a superficial to a
deeper sleep. Most people don't even get
close to the capacity of what they
really need with the deep restful sleep.
This affects metabolism. It affects
insulin. It affects blood sugar, but it
really affects a person's mood, anxiety,
depression. I mean, I've had patients
who ate perfectly, exercised
consistently, but they didn't sleep
well, and that's the thing that stopped
them from losing weight. There's also a
lot of data on this. I'm going to put
some research down below. Brighter
nighttime light exposure and risk for
type 2 diabetes. When you're outside
during the day in the sun getting the
bright light, this is what your body
needs. And even your blood sugars will
be better just from that. Regardless of
what you eat, it's going to help your
blood sugar to a certain degree. Whereas
evening bright lights worsen your blood
sugar. And then on top of that, at
night, what do people do? They snack.
They graze. Terrible, deadly
combination. So, in other words, light
can have a huge impact on your
metabolism. Now, if you've ever visited
someone in the ICU or you yourself been
in an ICU, you notice that they always
keep the lights on like 24/7 and they
kind of come in and check on the person
every couple hours. I know I was there
one time and literally all night long
they're waking me up, checking on me and
literally I had the light on. It's a
terrible environment for recovery.
There's something called ICU acquired
delirium as a circadian rhythm disorder.
Now, certain hospitals are starting to
use dynamic lighting. Hopefully, all of
them will get on board, but it's a big
issue. When the darkness disappears,
your brain destabilizes. And if you
really want to see a situation where
that night is removed completely, look
at institutions that have 247
lighting, prisons. You talk about severe
sleep deprivation, mood disorders that
come from that. This is why constant or
chronic lighting is considered
psychologically harmful. The brain
desperately needs night darkness just as
much as it needs light in the sun.
Humans have evolved with a lot of
contrast and in modern day that's pretty
much gone. This is called an ancestral
mismatch. I have a free download that I
want to give to you. This free download
is my daily routine in a checklist. This
is the routine that I use every day to
feel like I'm 18 years old even though
I'm 60 years old. And I want to give it
to you for free. And so there's a little
link down below. Click it and definitely
download that. So the fix for this is
not a supplement. It's not discipline.
It's not even an environmental
correction. Rule number one, make your
days aggressively bright. Get outside
before noon and expose yourself to sun.
I'm not talking about being burned, but
just get out there and get more sun. And
I would also be hesitant about wearing
sunglasses because you need some of that
light to get into the eye. And I'm not
talking about looking into the sun, but
just maybe to the side. It's okay to
squint. If you're not squinting, then
you're doing it wrong. But some of that
light needs to get inside the eye, okay?
From an angle, okay? Not directly right
into the retina. But even cloudy days
will work because you are going to be
getting certain amounts of light through
clouds. Not to the same lux, but you'll
get something. Number two, make night
genuinely dark. No overhead lights. Just
turn the overhead lights off. You might
want to get a couple lights around your
room that are like soft and like amber.
Make your screens dim, especially 3
hours before you go to bed. Now, if you
have a fireplace, realize that you're
going to get very small amounts of lux.
Rule number three, fix both ends of this
contrast scale. You want the first part
of your day to have bright light. Okay?
Now, certain times of the year when it's
cold out, you're going to be inside. So,
in that case, get a bright fullsp
spectrum light box or something above
your computer. I have one and I have
that turned on in the first part of the
day so you can actually get some bright
light. It's going to send a signal to
your eyes and tell your body to wake up.
And then at night, what I do is I
replace my light bulbs with incandescent
lights, which is much better. It's very
low lux and they're kind of dimmed and
they're really hard to get nowadays, but
if you can find them, that'd be great.
Just realize modern disease is not just
created by what we eat, but it's also
other things, too. And light is right
there at the top of the list. Make sure
when you go in your room that you don't
have these little lights around, and
maybe you might have a charger with a
light on it. Cover up those lights. This
is probably the lowest hanging fruit,
the easiest thing to do to create the
biggest impact on not just how long you
sleep, but the quality of sleep, how
deep you sleep, how you feel, your mood,
how you feel when you wake up, your
metabolism, your hormones, your
cognitive function. Because the lack of
contrast
creates the opposite effect. Now, since
I'm talking about light, I did an
interview with this doctor on light that
is literally mind-blowing the benefit of
sunlight. If you haven't seen that, you
have to watch it. I put that video up
right here. Check it out.